<chapter id="persistent-classes">
    <title>Persistent Classes</title>

    <para>
        Persistent classes are classes in an application that implement the entities
        of the business problem (e.g. Customer and Order in an E-commerce application).
        Persistent classes have, as the name implies, transient and also persistent
        instance stored in the database.
    </para>

    <para>
        NHibernate works best if these classes follow some simple rules, also known
        as the Plain Old CLR Object (POCO) programming model.
    </para>

    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-poco">
        <title>A simple POCO example</title>

        <para>
            Most .NET applications require a persistent class representing felines.
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[using System;
using Iesi.Collections;

namespace Eg
{
    public class Cat
    {
        private long id; // identifier
        private string name;
        private DateTime birthdate;
        private Cat mate;
        private ISet kittens
        private Color color;
        private char sex;
        private float weight;
    
        public virtual long Id
        {
            get { return id; }
            set { id = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual string Name
        {
            get { return name; }
            set { name = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual Cat Mate
        {
            get { return mate; }
            set { mate = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual DateTime Birthdate
        {
            get { return birthdate; }
            set { birthdate = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual float Weight
        {
            get { return weight; }
            set { weight = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual Color Color
        {
            get { return color; }
            set { color = value; }
        }
    
        public virtual ISet Kittens
        {
            get { return kittens; }
            set { kittens = value; }
        }
    
        // AddKitten not needed by NHibernate
        public virtual void AddKitten(Cat kitten)
        {
            kittens.Add(kitten);
        }
    
        public virtual char Sex
        {
            get { return sex; }
            set { sex = value; }
        }
    }
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            There are four main rules to follow here:
        </para>


        <sect2 id="persistent-classes-poco-accessors">
            <title>Declare accessors and mutators for persistent fields</title>

            <para>
                <literal>Cat</literal> declares accessor methods for all its persistent fields.
                Many other ORM tools directly persist instance variables. We believe 
                it is far better to decouple this implementation detail from the persistence 
                mechanism. NHibernate persists properties, using their getter and setter methods.
            </para>

            <para>
                Properties need <emphasis>not</emphasis> be declared public - NHibernate can
                persist a property with an <literal>internal</literal>, <literal>protected</literal>,
                <literal>protected internal</literal> or <literal>private</literal> visibility.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="persistent-classes-poco-constructor">
            <title>Implement a default constructor</title>

            <para>
                <literal>Cat</literal> has an implicit default (no-argument) constructor. All 
                persistent classes must have a default constructor (which may be non-public) so 
                NHibernate can instantiate them using <literal>Activator.CreateInstance()</literal>.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="persistent-classes-poco-identifier">
            <title>Provide an identifier property (optional)</title>

            <para>
                <literal>Cat</literal> has a property called <literal>Id</literal>. This property 
                holds the primary key column of a database table. The property might have been called 
                anything, and its type might have been any primitive type, <literal>string</literal>
                or <literal>System.DateTime</literal>. (If your legacy database table has composite
                keys, you can even use a user-defined class with properties of these types - see the
                section on composite identifiers below.)
            </para>

            <para>
                The identifier property is optional. You can leave it off and let NHibernate keep track 
                of object identifiers internally. However, for many applications it is still
                a good (and very popular) design decision.
            </para>

            <para>
                What's more, some functionality is available only to classes which declare an
                identifier property:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Cascaded updates (see "Lifecycle Objects")
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>ISession.SaveOrUpdate()</literal>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
                We recommend you declare consistently-named identifier properties on persistent
                classes.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="persistent-classes-poco-sealed">
            <title>Prefer non-sealed classes and virtual methods (optional)</title>
            <para>
                A central feature of NHibernate, <emphasis>proxies</emphasis>, depends upon the
                persistent class being non-sealed and all its public methods, properties and
                events declared as virtual. Another possibility is for the class to implement
                an interface that declares all public members.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can persist <literal>sealed</literal> classes that do not implement an interface
                and don't have virtual members with NHibernate, but you won't be able to use proxies
                - which will limit your options for performance tuning.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-inheritance">
        <title>Implementing inheritance</title>

        <para>
            A subclass must also observe the first and second rules. It inherits its
            identifier property from <literal>Cat</literal>.
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[using System;
namespace Eg
{
    public class DomesticCat : Cat
    {
        private string name;

        public virtual string Name
        {
            get { return name; }
            set { name = value; }
        }
    }
}]]></programlisting>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-equalshashcode">
        <title>Implementing <literal>Equals()</literal> and <literal>GetHashCode()</literal></title>

        <para>
            You have to override the <literal>Equals()</literal> and <literal>GetHashCode()</literal>
            methods if you intend to mix objects of persistent classes (e.g. in an <literal>ISet</literal>).
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis>This only applies if these objects are loaded in two different
            <literal>ISession</literal>s, as NHibernate only guarantees identity (<literal> a == b </literal>,
            the default implementation of <literal>Equals()</literal>) inside a single
            <literal>ISession</literal>!</emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>
            Even if both objecs <literal>a</literal> and <literal>b</literal> are the same database row
            (they have the same primary key value as their identifier), we can't guarantee that they are
            the same object instance outside of a particular <literal>ISession</literal> context.
        </para>

        <para>
            The most obvious way is to implement <literal>Equals()</literal>/<literal>GetHashCode()</literal>
            by comparing the identifier value of both objects. If the value is the same, both must
            be the same database row, they are therefore equal (if both are added to an <literal>ISet</literal>,
            we will only have one element in the <literal>ISet</literal>). Unfortunately, we can't use that
            approach. NHibernate will only assign identifier values to objects that are persistent,
            a newly created instance will not have any identifier value! We recommend implementing
            <literal>Equals()</literal> and <literal>GetHashCode()</literal> using
            <emphasis>Business key equality</emphasis>.
        </para>

        <para>
            Business key equality means that the <literal>Equals()</literal>
            method compares only the properties that form the business key, a key that would
            identify our instance in the real world (a <emphasis>natural</emphasis> candidate key):
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[public class Cat
{

    ...
    public override bool Equals(object other)
    {
        if (this == other) return true;
        
        Cat cat = other as Cat;
        if (cat == null) return false; // null or not a cat

        if (Name != cat.Name) return false;
        if (!Birthday.Equals(cat.Birthday)) return false;

        return true;
    }

    public override int GetHashCode()
    {
        unchecked
        {
            int result;
            result = Name.GetHashCode();
            result = 29 * result + Birthday.GetHashCode();
            return result;
        }
    }

}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Keep in mind that our candidate key (in this case a composite of name and birthday)
            has to be only valid for a particular comparison operation (maybe even only in a
            single use case). We don't need the stability criteria we usually apply to a real
            primary key!
        </para>

    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-dynamicmodels">
        <title>Dynamic models</title>
        
        <para>
            <emphasis>Note that the following features are currently considered
                experimental and may change in the near future.</emphasis>
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Persistent entities don't necessarily have to be represented as POCO classes
            at runtime. NHibernate also supports dynamic models
            (using <literal>Dictionaries</literal> of <literal>Dictionary</literal>s at runtime) . With this approach, you don't
            write persistent classes, only mapping files.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            By default, NHibernate works in normal POCO mode. You may set a default entity
            representation mode for a particular <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> using the
            <literal>default_entity_mode</literal> configuration option (see
            <xref linkend="configuration-optional-properties"/>.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The following examples demonstrates the representation using <literal>Map</literal>s (Dictionary).
            First, in the mapping file, an <literal>entity-name</literal> has to be declared
            instead of (or in addition to) a class name:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<hibernate-mapping>

    <class entity-name="Customer">

        <id name="id"
            type="long"
            column="ID">
            <generator class="sequence"/>
        </id>

        <property name="name"
            column="NAME"
            type="string"/>

        <property name="address"
            column="ADDRESS"
            type="string"/>

        <many-to-one name="organization"
            column="ORGANIZATION_ID"
            class="Organization"/>

        <bag name="orders"
            inverse="true"
            lazy="false"
            cascade="all">
            <key column="CUSTOMER_ID"/>
            <one-to-many class="Order"/>
        </bag>

    </class>
    
</hibernate-mapping>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            
            Note that even though associations are declared using target class names,
            the target type of an associations may also be a dynamic entity instead
            of a POCO.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            After setting the default entity mode to <literal>dynamic-map</literal>
            for the <literal>ISessionFactory</literal>, we can at runtime work with
            <literal>Dictionaries</literal> of <literal>Dictionaries</literal>:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[Session s = OpenSession();
Transaction tx = s.BeginTransaction();
ISession s = OpenSession();

// Create a customer
var frank = new Dictionary<string, object>();
frank["name"] = "Frank";

// Create an organization
var foobar = new Dictionary<string, object>();
foobar["name"] = "Foobar Inc.";

// Link both
frank["organization"] =  foobar;

// Save both
s.Save("Customer", frank);
s.Save("Organization", foobar);

tx.Commit();
s.Close();]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            The advantages of a dynamic mapping are quick turnaround time for prototyping
            without the need for entity class implementation. However, you lose compile-time
            type checking and will very likely deal with many exceptions at runtime. Thanks
            to the NHibernate mapping, the database schema can easily be normalized and sound,
            allowing to add a proper domain model implementation on top later on.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Entity representation modes can also be set on a per <literal>ISession</literal>
            basis:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[Session dynamicSession = pocoSession.GetSession(EntityMode.Map);

// Create a customer
var frank = new Dictionary<string, object>();
frank["name"] = "Frank";
dynamicSession.Save("Customer", frank);
...
dynamicSession.Flush();
dynamicSession.Close()
...
// Continue on pocoSession
]]></programlisting>
        
        
        <para>
            Please note that the call to <literal>GetSession()</literal> using an
            <literal>EntityMode</literal> is on the <literal>ISession</literal> API, not the
            <literal>ISessionFactory</literal>. That way, the new <literal>ISession</literal>
            shares the underlying ADO connection, transaction, and other context
            information. This means you don't have tocall <literal>Flush()</literal>
            and <literal>Close()</literal> on the secondary <literal>ISession</literal>, and
            also leave the transaction and connection handling to the primary unit of work.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-tuplizers" revision="1">
        <title>Tuplizers</title>
        
        <para>
            <literal>NHibernate.Tuple.Tuplizer</literal>, and its sub-interfaces, are responsible
            for managing a particular representation of a piece of data, given that representation's
            <literal>NHibernate.EntityMode</literal>.  If a given piece of data is thought of as
            a data structure, then a tuplizer is the thing which knows how to create such a data structure
            and how to extract values from and inject values into such a data structure.  For example,
            for the POCO entity mode, the correpsonding tuplizer knows how create the POCO through its
            constructor and how to access the POCO properties using the defined property accessors.
            There are two high-level types of Tuplizers, represented by the
            <literal>NHibernate.Tuple.Entity.IEntityTuplizer</literal> and <literal>NHibernate.Tuple.Component.IComponentTuplizer</literal>
            interfaces.  <literal>IEntityTuplizer</literal>s are responsible for managing the above mentioned
            contracts in regards to entities, while <literal>IComponentTuplizer</literal>s do the same for
            components.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Users may also plug in their own tuplizers.  Perhaps you require that a <literal>System.Collections.IDictionary</literal>
            implementation other than <literal>System.Collections.Hashtable</literal> be used while in the
            dynamic-map entity-mode; or perhaps you need to define a different proxy generation strategy
            than the one used by default.  Both would be achieved by defining a custom tuplizer
            implementation.  Tuplizers definitions are attached to the entity or component mapping they
            are meant to manage.  Going back to the example of our customer entity:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<hibernate-mapping>
    <class entity-name="Customer">
        <!--
            Override the dynamic-map entity-mode
            tuplizer for the customer entity
        -->
        <tuplizer entity-mode="dynamic-map"
                class="CustomMapTuplizerImpl"/>

        <id name="id" type="long" column="ID">
            <generator class="sequence"/>
        </id>

        <!-- other properties -->
        ...
    </class>
</hibernate-mapping>


public class CustomMapTuplizerImpl:
        NHibernate.Tuple.Entity.DynamicMapEntityTuplizer {
    // override the BuildInstantiator() method to plug in our custom map...
   protected override IInstantiator BuildInstantiator(
            NHibernate.Mapping.PersistentClass mappingInfo) {
        return new CustomMapInstantiator( mappingInfo );
    }

    private static final class CustomMapInstantiator:
            NHibernate.Tuple.DynamicMapInstantiator {
        // override the generateMap() method to return our custom map...
	    protected override IDictionary GenerateMap() {
		    return new CustomMap();
	    }
    }
}]]></programlisting>
        
        
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-lifecycle">
        <title>Lifecycle Callbacks</title>

        <para>
            Optionally, a persistent class might implement the interface 
            <literal>ILifecycle</literal> which provides some callbacks that allow
            the persistent object to perform necessary initialization/cleanup after
            save or load and before deletion or update.
        </para>

        <para>
            <!-- TODO: add xref to interceptor -->
            The NHibernate <literal>IInterceptor</literal> offers a less intrusive
            alternative, however.
        </para>

        <programlistingco>
            <areaspec>
                <area id="lifecycle1" coords="2 70"/>
                <area id="lifecycle2" coords="3 70" />
                <area id="lifecycle3" coords="4 70"/>
                <area id="lifecycle4" coords="5 70" />
            </areaspec>                        
            <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface ILifecycle
{
        LifecycleVeto OnSave(ISession s);
        LifecycleVeto OnUpdate(ISession s);
        LifecycleVeto OnDelete(ISession s);
        void OnLoad(ISession s, object id);
}]]></programlisting>
            <calloutlist>
                <callout arearefs="lifecycle1">
                    <para>
                        <literal>OnSave</literal> - called just before the object is saved or
                        inserted
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="lifecycle2">
                    <para>
                        <literal>OnUpdate</literal> - called just before an object is updated 
                        (when the object is passed to <literal>ISession.Update()</literal>)
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="lifecycle3">
                    <para>
                        <literal>OnDelete</literal> - called just before an object is deleted
                    </para>
                </callout>
                <callout arearefs="lifecycle4">
                    <para>
                        <literal>OnLoad</literal> - called just after an object is loaded
                    </para>
                </callout>                
            </calloutlist>
        </programlistingco>
        
        <para>
            <literal>OnSave()</literal>, <literal>OnDelete()</literal> and
            <literal>OnUpdate()</literal> may be used to cascade saves and
            deletions of dependent objects. This is an alternative to declaring cascaded
            operations in the mapping file. <literal>OnLoad()</literal> may
            be used to initialize transient properties of the object from its persistent
            state. It may not be used to load dependent objects since the
            <literal>ISession</literal> interface may not be invoked from
            inside this method. A further intended usage of <literal>OnLoad()</literal>, 
            <literal>OnSave()</literal> and <literal>OnUpdate()</literal> is to store a 
            reference to the current <literal>ISession</literal> for later use.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Note that <literal>OnUpdate()</literal> is not called every time the object's
            persistent state is updated. It is called only when a transient object is passed
            to <literal>ISession.Update()</literal>.
        </para>

        <para>
            If <literal>OnSave()</literal>, <literal>OnUpdate()</literal> or
            <literal>OnDelete()</literal> return <literal>LifecycleVeto.Veto</literal>, the operation is 
            silently vetoed. If a <literal>CallbackException</literal> is thrown, the operation 
            is vetoed and the exception is passed back to the application.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note that <literal>OnSave()</literal> is called after an identifier is assigned to 
            the object, except when native key generation is used.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="persistent-classes-validatable">
        <title>IValidatable callback</title>

        <para>
            If the persistent class needs to check invariants before its state is
            persisted, it may implement the following interface:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[public interface IValidatable
{
        void Validate();
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The object should throw a <literal>ValidationFailure</literal> if an invariant 
            was violated. An instance of <literal>Validatable</literal> should not change 
            its state from inside <literal>Validate()</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Unlike the callback methods of the <literal>ILifecycle</literal> interface, 
            <literal>Validate()</literal> might be called at unpredictable times. The
            application should not rely upon calls to <literal>Validate()</literal> for
            business functionality.
        </para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>
