<preface id="preface" revision="1">
	<title>Preface</title>

	<para>
		Working with object-oriented software and a relational database can be cumbersome
		and time consuming in today's enterprise environments. NHibernate is an object/relational
		mapping tool for .NET environments. The term object/relational mapping (ORM) refers to
		the technique of mapping a data representation from an object model to a relational
		data model with a SQL-based schema.
	</para>

	<para>
		NHibernate not only takes care of the mapping from .NET classes to
		database tables (and from .NET data types to SQL data types), but also provides data
		query and retrieval facilities and can significantly reduce development time otherwise
		spent with manual data handling in SQL and ADO.NET.
	</para>

	<para>
		NHibernate's goal is to relieve the developer from 95 percent of common data persistence
		related programming tasks. NHibernate may not be the best solution for data-centric
		applications that only use stored-procedures to implement the business logic in the
		database, it is most useful with object-oriented domain models and business logic in
		the .NET-based middle-tier. However, NHibernate can certainly help you to remove or
		encapsulate vendor-specific SQL code and will help with the common task of result set
		translation from a tabular representation to a graph of objects.
	</para>

	<para>
		If you are new to NHibernate and Object/Relational Mapping or even .NET Framework,
		please follow these steps:
	</para>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Read <xref linkend="quickstart"/> for a 30 minute tutorial,
				using Internet Information Services (IIS) web server.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Read <xref linkend="architecture"/> to understand the environments where
				NHibernate can be used.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Use this reference documentation as your primary source of information.
				Consider reading <emphasis>Hibernate in Action</emphasis>
				(java <ulink url="http://www.manning.com/bauer/" />)
				or <emphasis>NHibernate in Action</emphasis>
				(<ulink url="http://www.manning.com/kuate/" />)
        or <emphasis>NHibernate 3.0 Cookbook</emphasis>
        (<ulink url="https://www.packtpub.com/nhibernate-3-0-cookbook/book" />)
        or <emphasis>NHibernate 2 Beginner's Guide</emphasis>
        (<ulink url="http://www.packtpub.com/nhibernate-2-x-beginners-guide/book" />)if you need more help
        with application design or if you prefer a step-by-step tutorial. Also visit
        <ulink url="http://nhibernate.sourceforge.net/NHibernateEg/" /> for NHibernate
				tutorial with examples.
			</para>
		</listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        FAQs are answered on the <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/nhusers">NHibernate users group</ulink>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
			<para>
				The Community Area on the <ulink url="http://nhibernate.info/">NHibernate website</ulink> is a good source for
				design patterns and various integration solutions (ASP.NET, Windows	Forms).
			</para>
		</listitem>
	 </orderedlist>

	 <para>
		 If you have questions, use the
		 <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/nhusers">NHibernate user forum</ulink>.
		 We also provide a <ulink url="https://nhibernate.jira.com/">JIRA issue trackings system</ulink>
		 for bug reports and feature requests.
		 If you are interested in the development of NHibernate, join the developer mailing list.
		 If you are interested in translating this documentation into your language, contact us
		 on the <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/nhibernate-development">developer mailing list</ulink>.
	 </para>
</preface>
