<chapter id="quickstart">
    <title>Quickstart with IIS and Microsoft SQL Server</title>

    <sect1 id="quickstart-intro">
        <title>Getting started with NHibernate</title>

        <para>
            This tutorial explains a setup of NHibernate 1.0.2 within a Microsoft
            environment. The tools used in this tutorial are:
        </para>
        
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                Microsoft Internet Information Services (IIS) - web server supporting
                ASP.NET.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Microsoft SQL Server 2000 - the database server. This tutorial uses
                the desktop edition (MSDE), a free download from Microsoft. Support
                for other databases is only a matter of changing the NHibernate SQL
                dialect and driver configuration.
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                Microsoft Visual Studio .NET 2003 - the development environment.
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para>
            First, we have to create a new Web project. We use the name <literal>QuickStart</literal>,
            the project web virtual directory will <literal>http://localhost/QuickStart</literal>.
            In the project, add a reference to <literal>NHibernate.dll</literal>. Visual Studio
            will automatically copy the library and its dependencies to the project output directory.
            If you are using a database other than SQL Server, add a reference to the driver assembly
            to your project.
        </para>

        <para>
            We now set up the database connection information for NHibernate. To do this, open
            the file <literal>Web.config</literal> automatically generated for your project and add
            configuration elements according to the listing below:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<configuration>
    <!-- Add this element -->
    <configSections>
        <section
            name="hibernate-configuration"
            type="NHibernate.Cfg.ConfigurationSectionHandler, NHibernate"
        />
    </configSections>

    <!-- Add this element -->
    <hibernate-configuration xmlns="urn:nhibernate-configuration-2.0">
        <session-factory>
            <property name="dialect">NHibernate.Dialect.MsSql2000Dialect</property>
            <property name="connection.provider">NHibernate.Connection.DriverConnectionProvider</property>
            <property name="connection.connection_string">Server=(local);initial catalog=quickstart;Integrated Security=SSPI</property>
            
            <mapping assembly="QuickStart" />
        </session-factory>
    </hibernate-configuration>

    <!-- Leave the system.web section unchanged -->
    <system.web>
        ...
    </system.web>
</configuration>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The <literal>&lt;configSections&gt;</literal> element contains definitions of
            sections that follow and handlers to use to process their content. We declare
            the handler for the configuration section here. The <literal>
            &lt;hibernate-configuration&gt;</literal> section contains the configuration
            itself, telling NHibernate that we will use a Microsoft SQL Server 2000
            database and connect to it through the specified connection string.
            The dialect is a required setting, databases differ in their interpretation
            of the SQL "standard". NHibernate will take care of the differences and comes
            bundled with dialects for several major commercial and open source databases.
        </para>

        <para>
            An <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> is NHibernate's concept of a single
            datastore, multiple databases can be used by creating multiple XML
            configuration files and creating multiple <literal>Configuration</literal>
            and <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> objects in your application.
        </para>

        <para>
            The last element of the <literal>&lt;hibernate-configuration&gt;</literal>
            section declares <literal>QuickStart</literal> as the name of an assembly
            containing class declarations and mapping files. The mapping files
            contain the metadata for the mapping of the POCO class to a database table
            (or multiple tables). We'll come back to mapping files soon. Let's write the
            POCO class first and then declare the mapping metadata for it.
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="quickstart-persistentclass">
        <title>First persistent class</title>

        <para>
            NHibernate works best with the Plain Old CLR Objects (POCOs, sometimes
            called Plain Ordinary CLR Objects) programming model for persistent classes.
            A POCO has its data accessible through the standard .NET property mechanisms,
            shielding the internal representation from the publicly visible interface:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[using System;

namespace QuickStart
{
    public class Cat
    {
        private string id;
        private string name;
        private char   sex;
        private float  weight;

        public Cat()
        {
        }

        public string Id
        {
            get { return id; }
            set { id = value; }
        }

        public string Name
        {
            get { return name; }
            set { name = value; }
        }

        public char Sex
        {
            get { return sex; }
            set { sex = value; }
        }

        public float Weight
        {
            get { return weight; }
            set { weight = value; }
        }
    }
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            NHibernate is not restricted in its usage of property types, all .NET
            types and primitives (like <literal>string</literal>, <literal>char</literal>
            and <literal>DateTime</literal>) can be mapped, including classes from the
            <literal>System.Collections</literal> namespace. You can map them as values,
            collections of values, or associations to other entities. The <literal>Id</literal>
            is a special property that represents the database identifier (primary key) of
            that class, it is highly recommended for entities like a <literal>Cat</literal>.
            NHibernate can use identifiers only internally, without having to declare them
            on the class, but we would lose some of the flexibility in our application
            architecture.
        </para>

        <para>
            No special interface has to be implemented for persistent classes nor do we have
            to subclass from a special root persistent class. NHibernate also doesn't use any
            build time processing, such as IL manipulation, it relies solely on
            .NET reflection and runtime class enhancement (through Castle.DynamicProxy library).
            So, without any dependency in the POCO class on NHibernate, we can map it to
            a database table.
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="quickstart-mapping">
        <title>Mapping the cat</title>

        <para>
            The <literal>Cat.hbm.xml</literal> mapping file contains the metadata
            required for the object/relational mapping. The metadata includes declaration
            of persistent classes and the mapping of properties (to columns and
            foreign key relationships to other entities) to database tables.
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<hibernate-mapping xmlns="urn:nhibernate-mapping-2.0"
    namespace="QuickStart" assembly="QuickStart">

    <class name="Cat" table="Cat">

        <!-- A 32 hex character is our surrogate key. It's automatically
            generated by NHibernate with the UUID pattern. -->
        <id name="Id">
            <column name="CatId" sql-type="char(32)" not-null="true"/>
            <generator class="uuid.hex" />
        </id>

        <!-- A cat has to have a name, but it shouldn' be too long. -->
        <property name="Name">
            <column name="Name" length="16" not-null="true" />
        </property>
        <property name="Sex" />
        <property name="Weight" />
    </class>

</hibernate-mapping>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Every persistent class should have an identifer attribute (actually, only
            classes representing entities, not dependent value objects, which
            are mapped as components of an entity). This property is used to distinguish
            persistent objects: Two cats are equal if
            <literal>catA.Id.Equals(catB.Id)</literal> is true, this concept is
            called <emphasis>database identity</emphasis>. NHibernate comes bundled with
            various identifer generators for different scenarios (including native generators
            for database sequences, hi/lo identifier tables, and application assigned
            identifiers). We use the UUID generator (only recommended for testing, as integer
            surrogate keys generated by the database should be prefered) and also specify the
            column <literal>CatId</literal> of the table <literal>Cat</literal> for the
            NHibernate generated identifier value (as a primary key of the table).
        </para>

        <para>
            All other properties of <literal>Cat</literal> are mapped to the same table. In
            the case of the <literal>Name</literal> property, we mapped it with an explicit
            database column declaration. This is especially useful when the database
            schema is automatically generated (as SQL DDL statements) from the mapping
            declaration with NHibernate's <emphasis>SchemaExport</emphasis> tool. All other
            properties are mapped using NHibernate's default settings, which is what you
            need most of the time. The table <literal>Cat</literal> in the database looks
            like this:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[ Column |     Type     | Modifiers
--------+--------------+----------------------
 CatId  | char(32)     | not null, primary key
 Name   | nvarchar(16) | not null
 Sex    | nchar(1)     |
 Weight | real         |]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            You should now create the database and this table manually, and later read
            <xref linkend="toolsetguide"/> if you want to automate this step with the
            SchemaExport tool. This tool can create a full SQL DDL, including table
            definition, custom column type constraints, unique constraints and indexes.
            If you are using SQL Server, you should also make sure the <literal>ASPNET</literal>
            user has permissions to use the database.
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="quickstart-playingwithcats" revision="1">
        <title>Playing with cats</title>

        <para>
            We're now ready to start NHibernate's <literal>ISession</literal>. It is the
            <emphasis>persistence manager</emphasis> interface, we use it
            to store and retrieve <literal>Cat</literal>s to and from the database.
            But first, we've to get an <literal>ISession</literal> (NHibernate's unit-of-work)
            from the <literal>ISessionFactory</literal>:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[ISessionFactory sessionFactory =
            new Configuration().Configure().BuildSessionFactory();]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            An <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> is responsible for one database and
            may only use one XML configuration file (<literal>Web.config</literal> or
            <literal>hibernate.cfg.xml</literal>).
            You can set other properties (and even change the mapping metadata) by
            accessing the <literal>Configuration</literal> <emphasis>before</emphasis>
            you build the <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> (it is immutable). Where
            do we create the <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> and how can we access
            it in our application?
        </para>

        <para>
            An <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> is usually only built once,
            e.g. at startup inside <literal>Application_Start</literal> event handler.
            This also means you should not keep it in an instance variable in your
            ASP.NET pages, but in some other location. Furthermore, we need some kind of
            <emphasis>Singleton</emphasis>, so we can access the
            <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> easily in application code. The approach
            shown next solves both problems: configuration and easy access to a
            <literal>ISessionFactory</literal>.
        </para>

        <para>
            We implement a <literal>NHibernateHelper</literal> helper class:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[using System;
using System.Web;
using NHibernate;
using NHibernate.Cfg;

namespace QuickStart
{
    public sealed class NHibernateHelper
    {
        private const string CurrentSessionKey = "nhibernate.current_session";
        private static readonly ISessionFactory sessionFactory;

        static NHibernateHelper()
        {
            sessionFactory = new Configuration().Configure().BuildSessionFactory();
        }

        public static ISession GetCurrentSession()
        {
            HttpContext context = HttpContext.Current;
            ISession currentSession = context.Items[CurrentSessionKey] as ISession;

            if (currentSession == null)
            {
                currentSession = sessionFactory.OpenSession();
                context.Items[CurrentSessionKey] = currentSession;
            }

            return currentSession;
        }

        public static void CloseSession()
        {
            HttpContext context = HttpContext.Current;
            ISession currentSession = context.Items[CurrentSessionKey] as ISession;

            if (currentSession == null)
            {
                // No current session
                return;
            }

            currentSession.Close();
            context.Items.Remove(CurrentSessionKey);
        }

        public static void CloseSessionFactory()
        {
            if (sessionFactory != null)
            {
                sessionFactory.Close();
            }
        }
    }
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            This class does not only take care of the <literal>ISessionFactory</literal>
            with its static attribute, but also has code to remember the <literal>ISession</literal>
            for the current HTTP request.
        </para>

        <para>
            An <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> is threadsafe, many threads can access
            it concurrently and request <literal>ISession</literal>s. An <literal>ISession</literal>
            is a non-threadsafe object that represents a single unit-of-work with the database.
            <literal>ISession</literal>s are opened by an <literal>ISessionFactory</literal> and
            are closed when all work is completed:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[ISession session = NHibernateHelper.GetCurrentSession();

ITransaction tx = session.BeginTransaction();

Cat princess = new Cat();
princess.Name = "Princess";
princess.Sex = 'F';
princess.Weight = 7.4f;

session.Save(princess);
tx.Commit();

NHibernateHelper.CloseSession();]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            In an <literal>ISession</literal>, every database operation occurs inside a
            transaction that isolates the database operations (even read-only operations).
            We use NHibernate's <literal>ITransaction</literal> API to abstract from the underlying
            transaction strategy (in our case, ADO.NET transactions). Please note that the example
            above does not handle any exceptions.
        </para>

        <para>
            Also note that you may call <literal>NHibernateHelper.GetCurrentSession();</literal>
            as many times as you like, you will always get the current <literal>ISession</literal>
            of this HTTP request. You have to make sure the <literal>ISession</literal> is closed
            after your unit-of-work completes, either in <literal>Application_EndRequest</literal>
            event handler in your application class or in a <literal>HttpModule</literal> before
            the HTTP response is sent. The nice side effect of the latter is easy lazy
            initialization: the <literal>ISession</literal> is still open when the view is
            rendered, so NHibernate can load unitialized objects while you navigate the graph.
        </para>

        <para>
            NHibernate has various methods that can be used to retrieve objects from the
            database. The most flexible way is using the Hibernate Query Language (HQL),
            which is an easy to learn and powerful object-oriented extension to SQL:
        </para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[ITransaction tx = session.BeginTransaction();

IQuery query = session.CreateQuery("select c from Cat as c where c.Sex = :sex");
query.SetCharacter("sex", 'F');
foreach (Cat cat in query.Enumerable())
{
    Console.Out.WriteLine("Female Cat: " + cat.Name);
}

tx.Commit();]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            NHibernate also offers an object-oriented <emphasis>query by criteria</emphasis> API
            that can be used to formulate type-safe queries. NHibernate of course uses
            <literal>IDbCommand</literal>s and parameter binding for all SQL communication
            with the database. You may also use NHibernate's direct SQL query feature or
            get a plain ADO.NET connection from an <literal>ISession</literal> in rare cases.
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="quickstart-summary">
        <title>Finally</title>

        <para>
            We only scratched the surface of NHibernate in this small tutorial. Please note that
            we don't include any ASP.NET specific code in our examples. You have to create an
            ASP.NET page yourself and insert the NHibernate code as you see fit.
        </para>

        <para>
            Keep in mind that NHibernate, as a data access layer, is tightly integrated into
            your application. Usually, all other layers depend on the persistence mechanism.
            Make sure you understand the implications of this design.
        </para>

    </sect1>

</chapter>
